<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academia on Robert Vesco</title>
    <link>https://hugo.robertvesco.com/tags/academia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Academia on Robert Vesco</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language><atom:link href="https://hugo.robertvesco.com/tags/academia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Topic Models Network Analysis</title>
      <link>https://hugo.robertvesco.com/posts/topic-models-network-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hugo.robertvesco.com/posts/topic-models-network-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In preparation for a workshop at this year’s Academy of Management
conference my colleague &lt;a href=&#34;https://telfer.uottawa.ca/en/directory/tim-hannigan/&#34;&gt;Tim Hannigan&lt;/a&gt; and I gathered data on all the
sessions and workshops. We then processed them using R’s topic models
package to extract “themes” from the abstracts.The purpose was to
identify what the divisions at Academy were discussing and to look at
the overlap between them. The image below is one result from this work&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;In preparation for a workshop at this year’s Academy of Management
conference my colleague &lt;a href=&#34;https://telfer.uottawa.ca/en/directory/tim-hannigan/&#34;&gt;Tim Hannigan&lt;/a&gt; and I gathered data on all the
sessions and workshops. We then processed them using R’s topic models
package to extract “themes” from the abstracts.The purpose was to
identify what the divisions at Academy were discussing and to look at
the overlap between them. The image below is one result from this work&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://hugo.robertvesco.com/img/old/topic-models/Screenshot-from-2014-07-29-215955.png&#34;  alt=&#34;Mapping the relation between topics and Academy of Management Divisions&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;Mapping the relation between topics and Academy of Management Divisions&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What you see is a bipartite graph
which is essentially a network graph with two types of entities. In
this case our entities are AOM divisions (in black text encased in the
red blob) and topics (in blue text). The theme for this year’s
conference is the “Power of Words”. Thus, it’s fortunate that the
“Power Words” topic we identified from abstracts is squarely in the
center of the red blob. This means it’s a central theme relative to
the divisions. Thus, the divisions have done a good job of
incorporating the theme. Another interesting feature is that there are
divisions, such as HR/OB, TIM, OMT, that are central to topics. That
means that they are diverse with respect to themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outliers are located in complement of the intersection of the colored
blobs. Thus, divisions such OM (Operations Management) could be
considered outlying, and among topics, supply chain would be as
well. In this case, supply chain is the theme most linked to OM.  In
contrast, there are outlying themes, such as FirmPerformance, that are
strongly tied to central divisions. In this case, those divisions are
TIM, OMT and BPS — but not much else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, topic analysis is a cool way to identify themes in text and
opens up a lot of exciting possibilities. For instance, one neat thing
to do would be to look at how themes within Academy have changed over
the years.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
