<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Robert Vesco</title>
    <link>https://www.robertvesco.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Robert Vesco</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 21:36:35 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.robertvesco.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Review of Toby Ord&#39;s &#39;The Precipice: Existential Risk and the Future of Humanity&#39;</title>
      <link>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/toby-ord-the-precipice-existential-risk-future-humanity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 May 2025 21:36:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/toby-ord-the-precipice-existential-risk-future-humanity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Toby Ord writes a book that any human who cares about the future should read. &lt;em&gt;The Precipice&lt;/em&gt; is about all the things that could end humanity for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you thought we only needed to worry about climate change and nuclear war, you were wrong.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Toby Ord writes a book that any human who cares about the future should read. &lt;em&gt;The Precipice&lt;/em&gt; is about all the things that could end humanity for good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you thought we only needed to worry about climate change and nuclear war, you were wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are so many more nightmares out there that should be keeping you up at night. Ask most people and I doubt that super volcanoes, asteroids and stellar explosions come top of mind, but they got the dinosaurs! And according to Toby there&amp;rsquo;s a 1 in 1000 chance that in the next century one of these things could get us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newest kid on the block is unaligned AI. &amp;ldquo;Unaligned&amp;rdquo; is a fancy term for AI that won&amp;rsquo;t do our bidding and get &lt;em&gt;in line&lt;/em&gt; with the idea that we should be kept alive. What a euphemism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toby puts anthropogenic risks like AI, climate change, and war at a 1 in 6 chance that in the next century it will end us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put that in perspective, we have a 1 in 100 chance of dying in a car crash in our lifetimes, so 1 in 6 chance feels like a bit much. Hell, I don&amp;rsquo;t even like a 1 in 1000 chance for non-anthropogenic risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What are we currently doing about this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing really. Toby talks about the puny investments we are making in solving these risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And do we have humanity&amp;rsquo;s best people working on this? Of course not, they are in fact helping to build one of things that are most likely to kill us in the next 100 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s all very sobering, so what are we to do about it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toby takes a stab it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, he says, we need to focus on the existential risks. We need to get international institutions working on this. We need to use technology. We need to ramp up research. In essence, when your ship is sinking, you need to focus on plugging the hole before you can worry about whether the ship is sailing in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, if we survive this, the precipice, he says we need to take a break and reflect. He calls this the &amp;ldquo;long reflection.&amp;rdquo; This is the &lt;em&gt;eat, pray, love&lt;/em&gt; part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason we need to do all this is that we, as humans, have great potential. If we die, we will never know what our potential could be. It will be stolen from us like a child who died too soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s this part of the book that I like least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Toby does give some ideas about how to solve the problems and even suggests things that we can do as individuals, I find his approach both too sober given the stakes and not developed enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, he cautions people not to be too emotional lest we turn people away from the cause. But a 1/6 chance should be emotional. If your house was on fire, you would be screaming to make sure everyone got out in time. I&amp;rsquo;ve been in fire twice! I was in fact calm and sober the first time and I should not have been! Fortunately a german man in a speedo saved my life by knocking on my hotel door. Behind him were giant flames. A sight, literally, burned into my mind to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toby also wants to play nice with all the people who could be donors, but who are also driving us to extinction. The system, and it&amp;rsquo;s major players, are behaving irresponsibly. Who are they? Why are we so weak to stop them? Why aren&amp;rsquo;t more people capable of understanding these risks? How should we change these systems?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will never know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toby&amp;rsquo;s book tries to talk about our &amp;ldquo;great potential&amp;rdquo; but no one sacrifices their life for abstract ideas of great potential. So Toby highlights all the great things we have done as humanity and what&amp;rsquo;s left to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine if we could solve hunger and disease? What if we could solve injustice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about if we could make all the things we like about life: love, making babies, happiness and joy and have even more of them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, his argument sound dangerous close to that of techno-optimists like Marc Andressen: technology and science will solve all our problems. And humans are necessarily going to be upgraded to something better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But his vision rings hollow to me. The same as that of the techno-optimists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What should humanity be doing with itself? What should be our purpose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a question that everyone punts on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toby argues that we should deal with that in our &amp;ldquo;long reflection&amp;rdquo; - after we&amp;rsquo;ve vanquished our risks. He might be right, but perhaps the biggest risk of all is not AI or super volcanoes, but rather the fact that we haven&amp;rsquo;t set a shared goal and purpose that we are all willing to fight and live for. Because humans want more than mere survival - we want meaning and purpose - and when we don&amp;rsquo;t have it then what&amp;rsquo;s the point of living?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that said, I love this book and even if it only covered the existential risks and nothing more, it would still be worth reading by every human on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Prioritize Between Life and Work</title>
      <link>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/how-to-prioritize-between-life-and-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 10:48:39 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/how-to-prioritize-between-life-and-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most books on productivity focus on prioritization from the perspective of work. Sometimes they mention life issues, but it&amp;rsquo;s usually not the focus. As a result, I think too many of us overvalue work and undervalue the things that truly matter in life. Prioritization between work and life requires asking different questions and layering life before work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Most books on productivity focus on prioritization from the perspective of work. Sometimes they mention life issues, but it&amp;rsquo;s usually not the focus. As a result, I think too many of us overvalue work and undervalue the things that truly matter in life. Prioritization between work and life requires asking different questions and layering life before work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we take a biased sample of some of the most prominent productivity books, you&amp;rsquo;ll notice something peculiar:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bookshop.org/p/books/getting-things-done-the-art-of-stress-free-productivity-david-allen/15540042&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Getting Things Done&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bookshop.org/p/books/the-4-hour-workweek-escape-9-5-live-anywhere-and-join-the-new-rich-with-earbuds-timothy-ferriss/15562907&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 4-Hour Workweek&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bookshop.org/p/books/the-one-thing-the-surprisingly-simple-truth-about-extraordinary-results-gary-keller/266003&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The One Thing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people writing them tend not to have families, or are on their fourth marriage. This is not a judgment about their choices or lives, but simply an observation that their life experiences likely &lt;em&gt;prioritize&lt;/em&gt; certain activities over others. And to be clear, I’ve found the above books—and many others—extremely useful in both my work and personal life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there has always seemed to be a tension between work and personal life. Which is ironic, because all the books mentioned above emphasize making time for and thinking about what is essential and most important—yet what’s “most important” is almost always work-related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the biggest exception to this genre is Stephen Covey’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookshop.org/p/books/the-7-habits-of-highly-effective-people-30th-anniversary-edition-sean-covey/12583202&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 7 Habits of Highly Effective People&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;—which is perhaps not surprising, given that he had too many kids to count. His book, in contrast to many others, emphasizes &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; over merely &lt;em&gt;effective&lt;/em&gt;. Parenting examples feature prominently. This is something Scott Young of &lt;em&gt;Ultralearning&lt;/em&gt; also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/2024/11/19/10-important-books-productivity/&#34;&gt;noted&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the points Stephen Covey makes is to imagine your funeral. What would you want people to say about you? What kinds of relationships do you wish you had? This helps clarify what truly matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d argue that if most of us ran this exercise yearly, we’d be doing very different things with our lives than we are today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a somewhat similar vein is Jeff Bezos’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bQWr8ovbxF4&#34;&gt;Regret Minimization Framework&lt;/a&gt;: the idea being—will you regret this? Ironically, Bezos ultimately left his supportive spouse and the mother of his children for someone who does not appear to have been as supportive to him in the early years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder if reading Stephen Covey’s book would have given him additional guidance—beyond just doing what you might regret. Because what you might regret can be strongly influenced by the stage of life you’re in. Covey’s insight is that you need to work &lt;em&gt;with the end in mind&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I’m finding the following questions—a synthesis of the above books and several others—to be helpful in a tactical, day-to-day way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If the world ended tomorrow, what would I regret not doing?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This should be tied to your moral framework and thought of in both the short and long term.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If I could only do one thing, what would it be?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I like to look at this across my portfolio: family, health, finances, work, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which project or task would solve many others?&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is a leverage question. You can eliminate a whole slew of things with this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ironically, this question can help you get rid of work too, if it’s not aligned with your personal values and goals. Why are you even in this job?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, prioritizing life is hard—and we often take advice from good people who are part of the machine. And the machine wants you to work and put that first. But if you start with the end in mind, as Covey suggests, there is no better way to break out of the matrix.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AI Should Put Itself Out of a Job</title>
      <link>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/ai-should-put-itself-out-of-a-job/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 07:27:36 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/ai-should-put-itself-out-of-a-job/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I read a piece on linkedin from an entrepreneur who is encouraging his employees to use AI to put themselves out of a job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory an employee who follows that advice will then have the ability to move on to more interesting jobs and challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if his intentions were good, I&amp;rsquo;m sure what many of his staff were actually hearing was &amp;ldquo;you should train your replacement before we fire you&amp;rdquo;. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;I read a piece on linkedin from an entrepreneur who is encouraging his employees to use AI to put themselves out of a job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In theory an employee who follows that advice will then have the ability to move on to more interesting jobs and challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if his intentions were good, I&amp;rsquo;m sure what many of his staff were actually hearing was &amp;ldquo;you should train your replacement before we fire you&amp;rdquo;. &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as a leader, this sentiment is 100% true. As you&amp;rsquo;re growing your business, you need to slowly let loose of jobs so that you can focus on more important things a business needs. You need to automate, improve and delegate. And for any highly motivated individual this is probably good advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if we applied this idea to AI itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if the best AI would be the one that instead stealing our agency, helped us become stronger, more collaborative and self-sufficient?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/04/us/last-task-after-layoff-at-disney-train-foreign-replacements.html&#34;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/04/us/last-task-after-layoff-at-disney-train-foreign-replacements.html&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://www.robertvesco.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 11:41:40 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertvesco.com/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks for visiting my website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this site is to share my ideas around philosophy, technology, teaching and writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment I&amp;rsquo;m writing a book around sustainable happiness or what we must do to maximize happiness across generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m particularly concerned about the current trajectory of society and so I spend a lot time thinking about happiness, economics, technology and existential threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;m not writing, I&amp;rsquo;m teaching data science and related courses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Thanks for visiting my website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this site is to share my ideas around philosophy, technology, teaching and writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment I&amp;rsquo;m writing a book around sustainable happiness or what we must do to maximize happiness across generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m particularly concerned about the current trajectory of society and so I spend a lot time thinking about happiness, economics, technology and existential threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;m not writing, I&amp;rsquo;m teaching data science and related courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find me here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/robertvesco/&#34;&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/in/robertvesco/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://x.com/robertvesco&#34;&gt;https://x.com/robertvesco&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Could a Driver&#39;s License for the Internet Save Humanity?</title>
      <link>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/drivers-license-for-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/drivers-license-for-internet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The internet is destroying our civilization. And AI, with its ability to create fake content and exploit human weakness at scale, will only accelerate the the problem. However, there is an opportunity to turn this around if we use the motivation to get online to our advantage. In fact, harnessing this motivation has the capacity to do more for humanity than most schools. But first we need to treat the internet with the respect it deserves which means creating a something akin to a drivers license.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The internet is destroying our civilization. And AI, with its ability to create fake content and exploit human weakness at scale, will only accelerate the the problem. However, there is an opportunity to turn this around if we use the motivation to get online to our advantage. In fact, harnessing this motivation has the capacity to do more for humanity than most schools. But first we need to treat the internet with the respect it deserves which means creating a something akin to a drivers license.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating a driver&amp;rsquo;s license for the internet is not a new idea, but most of the proposals involve age and identity verification schemes.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; While these concepts are indeed important for protecting children and consumers, they don&amp;rsquo;t solve other types of problems and they create new ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Misinformation and tribalism remain rampant on the internet and the preferred solution so far is intrusive, abusive and untransparent censorship. We saw this during covid. If you asked the wrong questions, you suddenly would disappear off the internet.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the problem of addiction. We are addicted to the internet and our phones.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We&amp;rsquo;d rather stay in and watch netfix than have to interact with other humans. And not only are we addicted, but we are getting dumber and more tribal too.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to solve these problems and many more, we need to tier the internet into separate categories. To use a transportation analogy, getting a driver&amp;rsquo;s license to drive a car does not mean you&amp;rsquo;re ready to drive a tractor trailer or a plane. Those are fundamentally different vehicles. The internet is the same. Let&amp;rsquo;s consider some possible tiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tier 1: Consumer necessities, Government websites, Factual knowledge
Tier 2: Consumer wants, media, socials
Tier 3: Dangerous consumer products and media companies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tier 1 would be like walking or taking the subway. You don&amp;rsquo;t need a license for this. People should be able to get on the internet and interact with their goverments without any barriers. Tier 2 requires education to enable people to communicate logically and civilly. Tier 3 requires an even higher level of education. At this level you are flying. You need to show that you really know what you are doing to keep yourself and others safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the goal here is not to suppress free speech or impinge on privacy. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s quite the opposite. The goal is to educate people to develop critical thinking skills and communicate civilly with one another. With respect to privacy one could argue that it already doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist and whatever is left will go out the window with the advancements in AI anyway.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming our leaders are wise, which is a big assumption, I know, tier 3 could be gated. We know you went into that community, but we don&amp;rsquo;t track where you go after that. Would that really happen? Probably not, but again, I think that&amp;rsquo;s the best we could hope for from enlightened leadership. And even if we couldn&amp;rsquo;t get that at least the situation is transparent. Today, we have censorship and surveillance that hides in the unaccountable shadows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But where all of this could really take off is if we decide to use AI for good. Again, this is a big assumption. But AI has the capability of teaching people all the skills they need to defend themselves online and behave civilly. Not only could it teach people logical reasoning, rhetoric and safety, but it could do so in a way that is personalized and fun. It could do so at scale and repeat the education as much as necessary to help people access the tiers they want to access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And unlike regular school, people are very motivated to use the internet. They will jump through the hoops necessary to get their licenses. If we do this the right way, you could see a citizenry that understands how to think critically, avoid scams, manage their emotions and recognize cognitive biases. These skills are all foundational for living a good life and participating in healthy democracies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sum, combining the idea of a driver&amp;rsquo;s license for the internet with AI could be just the thing that could save our civilization and democracies from collapse, but we need to put education and freedom front and center rather than censorship, control and surveillance. And we need to remember that the internet is not a right but a privilege just like driving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/07/03/briefing/age-verification.html&#34;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/07/03/briefing/age-verification.html&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/zuckerberg-says-the-white-house-pressured-facebook-to-censor-some-covid-19-content-during-the-pandemic&#34;&gt;https://www.pbs.org/newshour/politics/zuckerberg-says-the-white-house-pressured-facebook-to-censor-some-covid-19-content-during-the-pandemic&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://fee.org/articles/the-government-s-sprawling-effort-to-censor-true-information-during-the-pandemic/&#34;&gt;https://fee.org/articles/the-government-s-sprawling-effort-to-censor-true-information-during-the-pandemic/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2024/02/do-you-have-a-phone-addiction&#34;&gt;https://hbr.org/2024/02/do-you-have-a-phone-addiction&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://thethirdtalk.org/chris-rock-talks-about-his-porn-addiction-in-standup-act/&#34;&gt;https://thethirdtalk.org/chris-rock-talks-about-his-porn-addiction-in-standup-act/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humanity is getting dumber &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.is/nycxV&#34;&gt;https://archive.is/nycxV&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brookings.edu/articles/technology-tribalism-and-truth/&#34;&gt;https://www.brookings.edu/articles/technology-tribalism-and-truth/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mamamia.com.au/true-crime-stories-rainpada-whatsapp-murders/&#34;&gt;https://www.mamamia.com.au/true-crime-stories-rainpada-whatsapp-murders/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/05/10-years-after-snowden-some-things-are-better-some-were-still-fighting&#34;&gt;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/05/10-years-after-snowden-some-things-are-better-some-were-still-fighting&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emacs for Data Science</title>
      <link>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/emacs-for-data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/emacs-for-data-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tl;dr:
If you want an editor that works with R, python, SAS, Stata, SQL and
almost any other data science language. If you want an editor with
IDE-like features. If you want an editor that works on any platform and
as well as on the terminal. If you&amp;rsquo;re a fan of literate
programming. If you want an editor that is highly customizable and
will be around after most editors have come and gone, then you&amp;rsquo;d be
hard pressed to find anything better than emacs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tl;dr:
If you want an editor that works with R, python, SAS, Stata, SQL and
almost any other data science language. If you want an editor with
IDE-like features. If you want an editor that works on any platform and
as well as on the terminal. If you&amp;rsquo;re a fan of literate
programming. If you want an editor that is highly customizable and
will be around after most editors have come and gone, then you&amp;rsquo;d be
hard pressed to find anything better than emacs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you work in exclusively in R, you might want to work in&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rstudio.com&#34;&gt;Rstudio&lt;/a&gt; . If
you work in python, you might be tempted by &lt;a href=&#34;https://code.google.com/p/spyderlib/&#34;&gt;Spyder&lt;/a&gt;. Chances are there
is a specialized IDE for whatever language you typically work in. But
that&amp;rsquo;s the rub. What if you want to work in another language? Or
combine languages? You end up using several IDEs, but not knowing them
well. Plus, once they fall out of favor or stop being updated, your
hard-gained knowledge is lost. At the other end of the spectrum there
are text editors like notepad++ and sublime. These work with just
about any language you can imagine and with some add-ons you can get
additional features, but they tend to be limited to certain platforms
and customization is often non-trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A modern data scientist often has to work on multiple platforms with
multiple languages. Some projects may be in R others in Python. Or
perhaps you have to work on a cluster with no gui. Or maybe you need to
write papers with latex. You can do all that with Emacs and customize
it to do whatever you like. I won&amp;rsquo;t lie though. The learning curve can
be steep, but I think the investment is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are some key features that I think make Emacs an excellent
editor for any data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;ide-like-features&#34;&gt;IDE-like features&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most programming languages, you get out-of-the-box syntax
highlighting. Packages like &lt;a href=&#34;http://ess.r-project.org/Manual/ess.html&#34;&gt;ESS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jorgenschaefer/elpy&#34;&gt;Elpy&lt;/a&gt; provide additional features
like autocompletion, documentation and debugging capabilities. The
number of IDE features available will vary by language, but at minimum
there is probably syntax highlighting and some form of autocompletion.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/emacs_autocomplete.png&#34;  alt=&#34;autocomplete in emacs&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;autocomplete in emacs&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the things that I enjoy is easy access to help and function
parameters &amp;hellip; which often also come with autocomplete.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/blog_R_help_syntax.png&#34;  alt=&#34;help for functions&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;help for functions&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;



  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/emacs_parameter_help.png&#34;  alt=&#34;parameter help for functions&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;parameter help for functions&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Enough with the print statements already and debug that R and python code!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/emacs_debug.png&#34;  alt=&#34;Interactive debugging with conditional breakpoint&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;Interactive debugging with conditional breakpoint&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the features that first sold me on Emacs was interactive
commands. With a keyboard short cut you can send a buffer, function,
paragraph or line to the interpreter. Let me be clear &amp;ndash; you don&amp;rsquo;t
even have to highlight the code. This saves you a ton of time when you&amp;rsquo;re
doing statistical analysis[fn:: Like many other features this will
depend on the package you install. That said, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to
implement this feature for your favorite language].&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/emacs_interactive.gif&#34;  alt=&#34;interactive&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;Interactive Commands&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;sql-too&#34;&gt;SQL too&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you work with databases? Many of the same benefits mentioned above
also apply to sql. Work with sqlite, postgresql, mysql and other databases
interactively. Do you have a long SQL statement you are debugging? No
problem. Iterate quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/emacs_sqlite.png&#34;  alt=&#34;Interactive SQL&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;Interactive SQL&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;org-mode--literate-programming&#34;&gt;Org mode / Literate Programming&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you write publications? Do you want to keep your code and paper
together? You a believer in reproducible research? With emacs you can
put any language you want in your document. While Rstudio allows this
also, you&amp;rsquo;re limited to just R and latex.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/emacs_literate.png&#34;  alt=&#34;Literate Programming&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;Literate Programming&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;do you need latex? No problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\frac{3}{4}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They key to this magic is a monster package called &lt;a href=&#34;http://orgmode.org/features.html&#34;&gt;org mode&lt;/a&gt;. It is one of
emac&amp;rsquo;s killer features. You can also use this to organize your code
&amp;hellip; or your life.&lt;/p&gt;
$$\frac{3}{4}$$&lt;h1 id=&#34;terminalremote-editing&#34;&gt;Terminal/remote editing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometime you need to remote into a server. Or perhaps you are working on a
cluster with no gui and you need to interactively debug your scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/emacs_terminal.png&#34;  alt=&#34;Emacs works in the terminal&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;Emacs works in the terminal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;interacting-with-the-shell&#34;&gt;Interacting with the shell&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there are terminal command you wish you could run? In emacs you can
run terminal commands easily. But what makes this feature super cool
is that it can operate on your text. You can select a region of code,
send it to a terminal command and have that stdout replace the text in
your buffer!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/emacs_shell.png&#34;  alt=&#34;Using SED to find and replace text&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;Use terminal commands to operate on text&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;rectangle-editing&#34;&gt;Rectangle editing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data scientists often work with tabular data. Sometimes you may want
to delete or move a column around. Or perhaps there is a block of
white space you need to change.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/emacs_rectangle.gif&#34;  alt=&#34;Using rectangle mode to alter blocks of text&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;Using rectangle mode to alter blocks of text&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h1 id=&#34;everything-at-your-finger-tips&#34;&gt;Everything at your finger tips&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs has numerous packages that allow you to search and find files,
functions and anything else that you can imagine. But by far the best
is helm. With just a few keys you can instantly find what you are
looking for. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t do it justice, but this demo gives you a taste
for the amazing things it can do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://tuhdo.github.io/helm-intro.html&#34;&gt;http://tuhdo.github.io/helm-intro.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any feature you want&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you&amp;rsquo;re wedded to sublime&amp;rsquo;s multiple cursors? You can get it:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://emacsrocks.com/&#34;&gt;http://emacsrocks.com/&lt;/a&gt;. Or perhaps you&amp;rsquo;re a long time vim user? Evil Mode
gives you the editing power of Vim with the utility of emacs. If you&amp;rsquo;re
a git user, Emac&amp;rsquo;s has magit which make working with git a joy. If there
is something that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have, check for pacakges, else emacs is the most customizable
editor you will find. Almost everything about it can be made to work
your particular work flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;30-years-old-and-a-large-user-base&#34;&gt;30+ years old and a large user base&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs has been around a long time. Code that was written a decade ago
mostly still work. And every year it&amp;rsquo;s getting better. However, emacs
24 is amazing. If you tried emacs years ago, you should give it
another try. It now has package management built in, so you can easily
add testing packages. Importantly, there is no sign that emacs is
going away anytime soon and it&amp;rsquo;s free. It will likely be around for at
least another decade if not more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;so-what-are-the-downsides&#34;&gt;So what are the downsides?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;legacy-code-on-the-intertubes-confuses-people&#34;&gt;Legacy code on the intertubes confuses people&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs has been around a long time. Emacs 24 was a huge improvement,
but it also broke a lot of things. Same goes for Org-mode between
versions 7 and 8. A lot of stuff on the intertubes will lead you
astray and frustrated if you&amp;rsquo;re not aware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;emacs-lisp-for-customization&#34;&gt;Emacs-lisp for customization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually enjoy working with lisp because it is so different from
other languages I work with. However, many others would prefer using a
language like python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;not-noob-friendly&#34;&gt;Not noob friendly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs is not like the cheerful, always smiling bro with the
abercrombie face. First encounters can be painful and awkward. It&amp;rsquo;s
not sublime. That said, there are several starter packages to enable
useful features out-of-the-box. For scientists, Kieran Healy&amp;rsquo;s starter
package might be useful:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://kieranhealy.org/resources/emacs-starter-kit/&#34;&gt;http://kieranhealy.org/resources/emacs-starter-kit/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another useful package is prelude: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bbatsov/prelude&#34;&gt;https://github.com/bbatsov/prelude&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re on a Mac, I&amp;rsquo;ve heard aquamacs will keep you warm and comfy:
&lt;a href=&#34;http://aquamacs.org/&#34;&gt;http://aquamacs.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these will give you the power of emacs, quickly. Personally, I
prefer to build my emacs up by scratch so it does what I want it to do
and no more. But these packages are great ways to get a feel for it&amp;rsquo;s
power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;multiple-packages&#34;&gt;Multiple packages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you decide you want to work with python be prepared to experiment
with lots of different python packages. While emacs has basic python
support, you probably want linting, refactoring or other useful
features. Many packages have tried to implement these features, some
better than others. Personally, I like Elpy, but it&amp;rsquo;s not perfect. The
downside of options is that you have to wade through them. It can be
painful sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-am-i-missing&#34;&gt;What am I missing?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I tried to include most of the features that I think would
appeal to data scientists, let me know if I missed any killer
feature and I&amp;rsquo;ll try to include it here.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/robertvesco&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/robertvesco&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting rid of manufacturing was a big mistake and Teece predicted it</title>
      <link>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/was-teece-prescient/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/was-teece-prescient/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Teece&amp;rsquo;s 1986 piece on profiting from innovation makes the following
claim:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trend in international business towards what Miles and
Snow call &amp;ldquo;dynamic networks&amp;rdquo; – characterized by vertical
disintegration and contracting – ought thus be viewed with
concern. (Business Week, March 3, 1986, has referred to the same
phenomenon as the Hollow Corporation.) &amp;ldquo;Dynamic networks&amp;rdquo; may not
so much reflect innovative organizational forms, but the
disassembly of the modern corporation because of deterioration in
national capacities, manufacturing in particular, which are
complementary to technological innovation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Teece&amp;rsquo;s 1986 piece on profiting from innovation makes the following
claim:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trend in international business towards what Miles and
Snow call &amp;ldquo;dynamic networks&amp;rdquo; – characterized by vertical
disintegration and contracting – ought thus be viewed with
concern. (Business Week, March 3, 1986, has referred to the same
phenomenon as the Hollow Corporation.) &amp;ldquo;Dynamic networks&amp;rdquo; may not
so much reflect innovative organizational forms, but the
disassembly of the modern corporation because of deterioration in
national capacities, manufacturing in particular, which are
complementary to technological innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dynamic networks may therefore signal not so much the rejuvenation
of American enterprise, but its piecemeal demise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over 20 years later, Andy Grove, co-founder and former Intel CEO, makes the following claim in a piece about how to bring jobs back to America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I believe the answer has to do with a general undervaluing of
manufacturing—the idea that as long as &amp;ldquo;knowledge work&amp;rdquo; stays in
the U.S., it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter what happens to factory jobs. It&amp;rsquo;s not
just newspaper commentators who spread this idea. Consider this
passage by Princeton University economist Alan S. Blinder: “The TV
manufacturing industry really started here, and at one point
employed many workers. But as TV sets became &amp;lsquo;just a commodity,&amp;rsquo;
their production moved offshore to locations with much lower
wages. And nowadays the number of television sets manufactured in
the U.S. is zero. A failure? No, a success.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I disagree. Not only did we lose an untold number of jobs, we
broke the chain of experience that is so important in
technological evolution. As happened with batteries, abandoning
today’s &amp;ldquo;commodity&amp;rdquo; manufacturing can lock you out of tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s
emerging industry.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CITES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teece, D. J. (1986). Profiting from Technological Innovation:
Implications for Integration, Collaboration, Licensing and Public
Policy. Research Policy, 15(6), 285–305. doi:16/0048-7333(86)90027-2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grove, A. (2010, July 1). Andy Grove: How America Can Create
Jobs. BusinessWeek: Magazine. Retrieved from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/10_28/b4186048358596.htm&#34;&gt;http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/10_28/b4186048358596.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dwoskin, E. (2012, October 18). How to Sell an Airplane in
China. BusinessWeek: Politics_and_policy. Retrieved from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessweek.com/articles/2012-10-18/how-to-sell-an-airplane-in-china&#34;&gt;http://www.businessweek.com/articles/2012-10-18/how-to-sell-an-airplane-in-china&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fishman, C. (2012, December). The Insourcing Boom. The
Atlantic. Retrieved from
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/print/2012/12/the-insourcing-boom/309166/&#34;&gt;http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/print/2012/12/the-insourcing-boom/309166/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Impact of Media on Entrepreneurship and Startups</title>
      <link>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/media-entrepreneurship-across-countries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/media-entrepreneurship-across-countries/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So there has been a lot talk about how the media hype machine is
setting entrepreneurs up for failure. That is, it’s
encouraging folks who may not be serious to try their hand at starting
a business when they probably shouldn’t. Below are some charts on the
relationship between media, legitimacy and entrepreneurship that
attempt to understand media’s impact.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;So there has been a lot talk about how the media hype machine is
setting entrepreneurs up for failure. That is, it’s
encouraging folks who may not be serious to try their hand at starting
a business when they probably shouldn’t. Below are some charts on the
relationship between media, legitimacy and entrepreneurship that
attempt to understand media’s impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data come from the Global Entrepreneurship Monitor‘s individual level surveys for years 2006-2008 where they survey folks from over 100 countries. Prior years did not have questions about media. There are about 250,000 individual level observations from nearly 50 countries in this particular analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intentions = Folks who are thinking about starting a business (i.e. business plan phase, talking about it)
Entry = Not just talk. They have either made some profits in the last 12 months or paid employees for at least 3.
Media = Have you seen success stories of new ventures in the public media?
Legitimacy = Is entrepreneurship a desirable career choice in your country?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are some descriptive statistics at the the country-level. The
countries are sorted by the percentage of individuals (using a random
sample) who saw success stories of new ventures in the public media. I
break it down by high and middle income countries as defined by the
World Bank. Eyeballing it, it appears there might be some sort of
relationship between media and intentions in middle income
countries. Again, this is just descriptive and it doesn’t control for
any other factors.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/old/entrepreneurship/CountryEntrybyMedia.png&#34;  alt=&#34;Entry by Country&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; &#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;Figure 1: Intention, Entry and Media&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Below is the interaction effect between the level of legitimacy of
entrepreneurship in a country and the media success stories of
entrepreneurship. I look at their joint impact on an individual’s
likelihood to have entrepreneurial intentions and entry into the
market. In this analysis, I control for as many relevant individual
and country-level factors as I can such as: age, education, wealth,
GDP, competitive pressure, property rights, and much more. The red and
blue colored symbols show where the effects are significant at the 95%
level.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/old/entrepreneurship/intgph_intention_entry_MediaXLegit_1SD_final.png&#34;  alt=&#34;Interaction Effects&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; &#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;Figure 2: Interactions&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In effect I am asking this question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we increase media by 1 standard deviation from the mean, how
might this affect an individuals’ intentions and entry contingent
on how cool entrepreneurship already is in their country?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One possible interpretation is that in countries where
entrepreneurship is not cool, media boosts entry more than intentions
on a relative basis. I say relative because in absolute terms the
number of people with entrepreneurial intentions is always greater
than those who actually succeed in entering the market and this
analysis looks at % not absolute numbers. Obviously, many people drop
out of entrepreneurship once reality hits them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, in countries where entrepreneurship is already cool, or
at least very acceptable, increasing media probably contributes to the
hype machine so intentions will increase more relative to entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So again, it may be that the media success stories of entrepreneurs
helps entrepreneurs in countries where entrepreneurship is not very
accepted, but less so in countries where it is already accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other thing to note is that media increases both intentions and
entry no matter what. So one might argue that who cares if media
creates hype that causes more people to have intentions than they
should. It also increases entry. So maybe that gal who was going to
join a hedge fund or consulting firm instead started her own business
and was successful… though success in this case is NOT in performance,
but simply in entry so I can’t say much about how successful they
truly were – only that they reached one particularly important
milestone. This is a limitation of the data.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topic Models Network Analysis</title>
      <link>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/topic-models-network-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.robertvesco.com/posts/topic-models-network-analysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In preparation for a workshop at this year’s Academy of Management
conference my colleague &lt;a href=&#34;https://telfer.uottawa.ca/en/directory/tim-hannigan/&#34;&gt;Tim Hannigan&lt;/a&gt; and I gathered data on all the
sessions and workshops. We then processed them using R’s topic models
package to extract “themes” from the abstracts.The purpose was to
identify what the divisions at Academy were discussing and to look at
the overlap between them. The image below is one result from this work&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;In preparation for a workshop at this year’s Academy of Management
conference my colleague &lt;a href=&#34;https://telfer.uottawa.ca/en/directory/tim-hannigan/&#34;&gt;Tim Hannigan&lt;/a&gt; and I gathered data on all the
sessions and workshops. We then processed them using R’s topic models
package to extract “themes” from the abstracts.The purpose was to
identify what the divisions at Academy were discussing and to look at
the overlap between them. The image below is one result from this work&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&#34;center&#34; &gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.robertvesco.com/img/old/topic-models/Screenshot-from-2014-07-29-215955.png&#34;  alt=&#34;Mapping the relation between topics and Academy of Management Divisions&#34;   style=&#34;max-width:100%; width:auto; margin:0px 0px 0px 0px;border-radius: 15px; -moz-border-radius:15;&#34;  /&gt;
    
      &lt;figcaption class=&#34;left&#34;  style=&#34;color: black;&#34; &gt;Mapping the relation between topics and Academy of Management Divisions&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
  &lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What you see is a bipartite graph
which is essentially a network graph with two types of entities. In
this case our entities are AOM divisions (in black text encased in the
red blob) and topics (in blue text). The theme for this year’s
conference is the “Power of Words”. Thus, it’s fortunate that the
“Power Words” topic we identified from abstracts is squarely in the
center of the red blob. This means it’s a central theme relative to
the divisions. Thus, the divisions have done a good job of
incorporating the theme. Another interesting feature is that there are
divisions, such as HR/OB, TIM, OMT, that are central to topics. That
means that they are diverse with respect to themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outliers are located in complement of the intersection of the colored
blobs. Thus, divisions such OM (Operations Management) could be
considered outlying, and among topics, supply chain would be as
well. In this case, supply chain is the theme most linked to OM.  In
contrast, there are outlying themes, such as FirmPerformance, that are
strongly tied to central divisions. In this case, those divisions are
TIM, OMT and BPS — but not much else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, topic analysis is a cool way to identify themes in text and
opens up a lot of exciting possibilities. For instance, one neat thing
to do would be to look at how themes within Academy have changed over
the years.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
